Guide to the Helen Vandervort papers, 1922-1994
Vandervort, Helen papers, 1922-1994
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Helen Vandervort papers, 1922-1994.
4378
Helen, Vandervort 1905-1994.
7 Cubic Feet.
Correspondence, financial records, reports, speeches, photographs, printed materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, financial records, reports, speeches, photographs, printed materials, certificates, and biography relating to Vandervort's work with the Tompkins County Public Library and the Finger Lakes Library System; the Tompkins County Senior Citizens' Council and senior citizens issues; the New York State College of Human Ecology; the New York State Fair; and women's rights issues. Also, letters from the Bull family (1922-26), interviews with Helen Vandervort by Eleanor Randles and Kathleen Babbitt.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Extension education administrator.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, financial records, reports, speeches, photographs, printed materials, certificates, and biography relating to her work with the Tompkins County Public Library and the Finger Lakes Library System; the Tompkins County Senior Citizens' Council and senior citizens issues; the New York State College of Human Ecology; the New York State Fair; and women's rights issues. Also, letters from the Bull family (1922-26), interviews with Helen Vandervort by Eleanor Randles and Kathleen Babbitt.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Vandervort, Helen, 1905-1994.; Babbitt, Kathleen, interviewer.; Bull family.; Randles, Eleanor Foster, 1920-, interviewer.; Alpha House (Trumansburg, N.Y.).; Cornell University--Alumni and alumnae.; Finger Lakes Library System.; New York State College of Human Ecology.; Tompkins County Public Library.; Tompkins County Senior Citizens' Council.; New York State Fair.
Subjects:
Home economics extension work.; Home economics extension workers.; Women--New York (State)--Ithaca.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Libraries and Miscellaneous
Box 1 Folders 1-42
Box 2 Folders 1-15
Series II. Senior Citizens
Box 2 Folders 18-29
Box 3 Folders 1-3
Box 4 Folders 1-2
Series III. Printed Material
Box 4
Series IV. Biographical Information
Box 5
Box 6 Folders 1-6
Series V. Correspondence
Box 6 Folders 7-41
Series VI. New York State Fair
Box 6 Folders 42-45
Series VII. Subject Files
Box 5 Folders 1-4
Box 7 Folders 1-43
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Libraries and Miscellaneous
  - Library Financial Records (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Library correspondence: Tompkins County Public Library and Finger Lakes Library System (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Finger Lakes Public Library System (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Friends of the Library (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Library dedication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tompkins County Public Library (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cornell Library Association (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Library - Study Team/Reference Team (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Library Contracts, Agreements, Proclamations (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Micellaneous correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Vandervort Christmas letters (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Flora Rose Fellowship (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - Flora Rose Scholarship (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - Flemmie Kittrell Fellowship (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Emily Atkers (aunt of Alfred Kahn) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Agda Osborn (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Vertrees Ackerly (cousin active in Home Bureau) (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Connie Cook (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jeanette B. McCay (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Meade Summers (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Nelson Rockefeller (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous local projects (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Route 96 controversy (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Doing Woman's History" - conference on research sources at Cornell, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Cooperative Extension miscellany (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Small projects (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Class of 1926 miscellany (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Elizabeth Cady Stanton Foundation (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Susan B. Anthongy coin (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Woman's Hall of Fame director's meetings (Box 1, Folder 37-40)
  - Woman's Hall of Fame catalogs (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
  - Libraries - general guidelines, other local libraries (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Library - donations (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Albany fund raising (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Woman's Community Building (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - New York State Department of Commerce Woman's Council (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - United Way (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hospital (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cornell University Council - membership (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gamma Sigma Delta (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Martha Van Rensselaer Hall - new wing (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Savage Hall - fund raising (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - New York State Fair (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Syracuse Music Museum (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous lectures (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Retirement from New York Sate Fair (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Speeches (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Certificates (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series II. Senior Citizens
  - Miscellany (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - RSVP (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cookbook for Two (draft) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Older Persons Records (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sorority (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Biography (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Jody Colerick (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Thesis: Adaptional Process in Later Life, by Elizabeth Jo Colerick (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Old letters, monographs, health bill (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
  - Older Persons Record (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Senior Citizen course taught at Elmira (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Nutrition for the Elderly - Title IV (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ruth Pond correspondence - Colbert, Shipherd, etc. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Senior Citizens and Aging Gray Panthers (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Office for the Aging (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Lansing Housing Authorities (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Material on Holland (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - New York State Health Planning Commission (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Right to Die (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Protective Services for Aged (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Legislation (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - White House Conference on Aging, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
  - Health care (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Vision care (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - Senior Citizens' Council reports (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Senior Citizens' Council - new buildings (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
  - Senior Citizens' Council evaluations (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Senior Citizens' Council Operations Manual (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Tompkins County Office for the Aging (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Housing for the elderly (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - State Plan for the Aging (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - New York State Office for the Aging (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - New York State Office for the Aging - Older Americans Act Program Committee (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Special items - letter to Gannett concerning funds to complete the payment for the Senior Citizen Center (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - New York State Older Americans Act (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Tompkins County Older Americans Needs Assessment Survey (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series III. Printed Material
  - Legislative Approaches to the Problems of the Elderly; A Handbook of Model State Statutes (Box 4)
  - The Golden Years...A Tarnished Myth (Box 4)
  - The Employment Problems of Older Workers (Box 4)
  - Serve: Older Volunteers in Communtiy Service (Box 4)
  - Report of the Advisory Committee on Service Centres for Old People - Netherlands? (Box 4)
- Series IV. Biographical Information
  - Cassette tape and Genealogy of William Bull-1984 (Box 5)
  - Resume, Photographs (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Achievements, 1960-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - High School Memorabilia (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1920-1979 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Congratulatory letters for Helen's receiving the Women of Achievement Award, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Same as above, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Series V. Correspondence
  - Obituary, Clippings, Correspondence concerning Helen Vandervort's death, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, clippings, photos concerning the Vandervort and Bull Families, 1950-1989 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Clippings concerning Amy Bull Crist - Helen's sister, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence concerning Harry Bull - Helen's uncle, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Condolences - death of Helen's Father, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Postcards to and from John and Helen Vandervort (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - from Helen's family to Helen, 1923-1948 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence written by Helen Vandervort, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence written by John Vandervort (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - from Helen's mother to Helen, 1924-01-1924-05 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence - from Helen's mother to Helen, 1925-06-1925-12 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - from Helen's mother to Helen, 1926, 1943, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence - from Helen's father to Helen, Undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence - from Helen's children, 1940-1959 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence - from various people, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence - from various people, 1925-1928 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence - from various people, Undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence - from famous people, 1920-1989 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, clippings, photos, concerning the Rockefellers, 1960-1979 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence - personal, 1940-1959 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence - personal, 1960-1989 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence - personal, 1960-1989 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence - personal, 1960-1989 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence - personal, 1960-1989 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence - personal, 1960-1989 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence concerning politics, 1960-1989 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence concerning Savage Hall, 1980-1989 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence with Shizuko Muto, 1980-1989 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence - concerning course at Elmira College, Antique Sale, Auction Channel 24, 1950-1989 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence - concerning students helped for Cornell Admission, 1960-1989 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence concerning job opportunities, 1920-1929, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence concerning MVR booklet by Percival, 1950-1969 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence concerning SUNY, 1960-1989 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence concerning Library Association, 1960-1969 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence with Jeanette McCay, 1980-1989 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Series VI. New York State Fair
  - New York State Fair material - including photos, Nelson Rockefeller letters, 1950-1979 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - New York State Fair material, 1960-1979 (Box 6, Folder 43-45)
- Series VII. Subject Files
  - Calendars, 1960-1989 (Box 5)
  - Alpha House - correspondence, clippings, minutes of meetings (Box 5)
  - Campus Master Plan and Response to the SUNY Master Plan to 1980 - College of Human Ecology (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - College Committee on Public Service and Continuing Education - suggested ways to expand continuing education in Human Ecology, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Guidelines for Field Experience - report, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Report of Admissions and Recruitment Activities, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Plan of Organization for the College of Home Economics from David Knapp, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Planning for the 1980s- from Jerome Zigler to Advisory Council, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - DNS- Philosophy Statement, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - DNS Goals and Plans 1981-1986, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Extracts from Dean's Mid-Year Report to Provost W.K. Kennedy- Jerome Zigler, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Occupations of Human Ecology Male Alumni, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Statement of College-Wide Goals and Priorities - Jerome Zigler, 1980-`986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Dean's Report to the Advisory Council (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Human Ecology Planning Document, 1980-`986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Proposal for Establishing a Master of Professional Studies Program in Health Administration in Human Ecology, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Alpha Xi Delta (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - American Association of University Women, 1950-1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - American Association of University (Fellows), 1950-1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - College of Human Ecology - correspondence, memos, 1960-1989 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - College of Human Ecology - correspondence, 1950-1989 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Human Ecology Advisory Council - background material relating to the last 10 year period, 1978-1988 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Early history of Human Ecology - MVR, Rose, Blanding - clippings and correspondence, 1940-1989 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Advisory Council material, 1960-1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Alumni meeting in Rochester to raise scholarship money, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Human Ecology- biographical material on Helen Vandervort, 1960-1989 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - letters and material concerning nutrition, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - William Wright correspondence - Human Ecology, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Commemorations (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Confederation of Alumni Associations Alumni Award, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Cornell Class of 1926 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Cornell "11" (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Dairyman's League Publications (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Empire State Theater and Music Society (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Finger Lake Library System, 1960-1979 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Corrine Brown Galvin (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Gamma Sigma Delta, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Gov. Conference on Women's Work and Women's Council, 1960-1979 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Home Bureau and Cooperative Extension - correspondence, memos, 1930-1979 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Hotel School - founding of it (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - International Fair, 1960-1969 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Ithaca Area Beautification, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Ithaca City Federation of Women's Organizations and Women's Community Building, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Ithaca - Northeast Senior Citizens, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Ithaca Public Library, 1960-1979 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Merril-Palmer Institute (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Office of the Aging, 1970-1989 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Oral History Transcript - Helen Vandervort (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Scholarships, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Flemmie Kittrell Scholarship, 1970-1989 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Flora Rose Graduate Fellowship, 1960-1979 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Helen Vandervort Scholarship, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Helen Vandervort Scholarship Recipients, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Human Ecology Fellowship, 1960-1989 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Jean Failing Fellowship, 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Speeches (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Ithaca and New York State Senior Citizens, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Women's Hall of Fame - MVR nomination, 1960-1989 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Youth, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Pins and Badges worn by Helen Vandervort (Box 7)